(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine and
today we're talking about weddings.
- That's right, we are having a wedding
but we're actually planning all
the things out for the wedding.
- That's right, so there are lots of things
to think about when
you're planning a wedding
and I don't think that the woman in
today's dialogue has forgotten anything.
Let's take a listen to the dialogue
first and we'll be back in a moment.
(upbeat music)
- Trina, will you marry me?
- Yes, yes, yes.
Jared of course I'll marry you.
- Oh babe, can't wait to spend
the rest of my life with you.
I can't wait for all
the adventures we're
gonna have for all the
fights and the laughter.
Can't wait to grow old
and wrinkly with you.
- Oh Jared, I can't wait for our wedding.
I hope you don't mind but
I've already chosen a date.
Six months from now in the
summer, Melissa saw you buying the
ring last month so I had
plenty of time to start planning.
- She what?
- Oh, don't worry, sweetie.
I didn't know when you
were going to propose.
It was still a nice surprise.
As I was saying, I got it all planned out.
There's always nothing left to do.
I wrote up our guest list and we will
have roughly 400 guests attending.
- 400?
- No need to sweat it.
My parents agreed to pay
for most of the wedding
which is going to be
a low budget anyway.
So roughly 400 people,
which means that the whole
at Northwood Heights
will be our reception venue.
I thought it would be nice if we had
the wedding at your parents' church
and my uncle of course
would be officiating.
We'll meet with him soon for
some pre-wedding counseling.
The music for the wedding
ceremony was a no-brainer.
My step sister and her string
quartet will take care of that.
My cousin will be the
official photographer.
I thought it would also be nice
if his daughter could sing a solo.
Did you know that she's
going to be professional
opera singer and then of
course the ladies at the church
would love to be our caters for the banquet
and will get the youth group to serve us?
I was thinking that your friend's band
could be our entertainment for the night.
So they might have to turn it
down a bit or we could hire a DJ.
Your sister's husband
could get us a discount
with that company that
does the decor at weddings.
What's their name again?
I was thinking that we
could have an island paradise
theme wedding and our
theme color would be a soothing
blue-like aqua marine and
there will be a huge seashell
on the wall behind the podium
where we'll make our toast.
What do you think of small packages
of drink mixes for our wedding favors?
Who else am I missing?
Oh, your uncle could be our florist and
his wife could make our wedding cake.
Oh, wow.
See, it's going to be wonderful.
Oh, this wedding is going to
be everything I ever dreamed of.
If I survive the next six months.
All right, we're back, so she talked a lot.
So there are a lot of words and phrases
here that we're going to take a look at.
So let's start with a couple of
them on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
All right, so on language takeaway,
why don't we start off with the first word?
And the basic one, before you start a
plan of wedding, the guy needs to propose.
Or the woman, let's be 21st
century here, normally it's the man.
But to propose in this instance
means to propose marriage.
So basically, this is the part
where someone gets down
on his knee and he says, you know,
sweetie pie, I want to be with you forever.
Will you marry me to propose?
So to propose is to ask
someone to marry you.
That's right.
But it can also mean
something else, right, to suggest.
That's right.
So I could propose an idea,
or I could propose a plan.
But in this case, to propose
has another meaning,
and it's basically to ask
someone to marry you.
Okay, very good.
So now we've proposed to someone.
So we need to start planning our wedding.
And I think one of the first
steps is you need to know
how many people are going to be
there and who you're going to invite.
That's right.
So when you're planning a
wedding, you have to think
about the people that are
going to attend the wedding.
So you prepare a guest list.
Okay, so a guest list.
Now it's pretty simple, right?
You have a list where
you put everyone's name
there and you know how
many people are coming.
Exactly.
Okay, a guest list.
Now you have your guest list
and now you need to pick a
place where your wedding will be.
That's right.
So we often talk about
two parts to a wedding.
The first part is the ceremony,
the wedding ceremony.
Maybe if you're religious,
that happens in a church.
Okay.
But there's a party afterwards.
And that's what we're talking about here.
We're talking about a reception.
Okay.
A reception is basically the party part
of the wedding where you drink and eat
and listen to music and dance.
Okay.
So obviously for that, you need a space.
In place to have the party and
we call it the reception venue.
Okay, a venue.
So as you said, the reception is the party
and the venue is the
place where you have it.
Now a venue is not a specific word, right?
You can use venue for
many different places.
That's right.
So for example, someone's having a concert,
I can ask him, hey, what's the venue?
Okay.
That means what is the theater?
Or where's this place you're
going to have the concert?
Okay.
For example, a stadium can be a
venue or a restaurant can be a venue.
Exactly.
So a venue is a place
where an event can be held.
Okay.
Very good.
So now we have our reception venue.
We have our guest list.
And the girl was talking
about her uncle officiating.
What does she mean by to officiate?
Okay.
So like you said, the
verb here is to officiate.
Her uncle will be officiating.
I mean, he will be the
person who marries them.
So maybe you've seen
movies before where there's a
priest who says, you know,
do you take this woman
to be your lawfully wedded
wife until death to you part?
Right.
That person who says that, the
person who asks the questions,
he or she officiates.
Okay.
officiates.
So that's basically the action of marrying
someone or leading the ceremony.
That's right.
And in America, this isn't just anybody.
Someone has to have
like a license or has to be a
priest and has to have
the authority to officiate.
Okay, very good.
So that's a very interesting
word there to officiate.
Now moving on, when we talk
about the food for the reception venue,
well, we need somebody
to cook it and prepare it.
And that's when we hire caters.
That's right.
So a caterer is kind
of like a cook, but a
caterer basically arranges
a meal for many people.
And usually the person
will bring the food to you.
So for example, if we're
gonna have a party mark
and we're gonna throw
it at a venue 10 miles
away, the caterer will
bring the food to us.
Okay.
Okay, so that's a caterer.
You get someone to cater your wedding.
That's right.
Or a caterer party.
So I've had parties before that I've
called caterers to make the food for.
So basically they work
with me and I tell them
the kind of food I would
like and they prepare it.
Okay, very good.
And now for our last part for the
wedding planning, you have the food,
you have the venue, you have everything,
but you also need to decorate a little bit.
And this is when you call a florist.
- Florist.
So this sounds a lot like flour,
florist flour and then that's, let's
basically what this person does.
A florist is a person who prepares flowers
or who cuts flowers and
uses them to decorate.
Okay, so you go to the florist to buy
flowers, roses and different types of things.
Okay, a florist, very good.
So six key words there that are
related to planning a wedding.
Why don't we move on now to a
couple of phrases on fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
All right, so this first
phrase is really good one.
It's a little bit gross.
We're talking about sweat.
The woman in this dialogue
says, hey, no need to sweat it.
So what does this mean?
- All right, so if you say to sweat means
when you are running,
you're doing exercise,
it's hot water starts to
come out of your skin.
- Yummy.
- Right, but if the person says, hey,
don't sweat it or no need to sweat it,
it's a colloquial way
of saying don't worry.
- Oh, okay, so we're not
actually talking about sweat here.
So maybe Marco, you and
I are working on a project
together and I say,
listen Marco, I'm so sorry.
I have a family emergency.
I can't finish the project with you.
Would you be able to help me out?
I'm so sorry.
- Sure, sure, don't sweat it.
It's not a problem.
- Okay, so don't worry.
- Don't worry.
Right, so if you tell someone to not sweat
it, don't sweat it or no need to sweat it
because you're basically telling
them, it's okay, it's not a problem.
Everything's gonna be fine.
- Great.
So the next phrase here
is also kind of relaxed.
It's kind of laid back.
So the woman is still describing
some of the things she's
prepared for the wedding and
she says, hey, listen, don't worry.
The music was a no-brainer.
Okay, no-brainer.
- Okay, this is really easy.
Well, your brain is
inside your head, right?
So if you say no-brainer, it's
basically saying you don't have
to think about it too much
or it's very easy, very simple.
- Okay, so I was deciding
on where to go on vacation
and the options were
Thailand or Antarctica.
That's a no-brainer, Thailand.
Obviously, I wanna go
where it's sunny and warm.
So a no-brainer means I didn't
even have to think about it.
It was that easy.
- Right, that's right.
- That decision-making was a no-brainer.
All right, so for our next phrase, the
girl was also talking about the music
and she was talking about a
band, maybe like a rock band
and she said, well, maybe they could
play but they would need to tone it down.
- Okay, so this is a
favorite phrase of parents
and all over the English-speaking
world, tone it down.
In this case, we're talking about music.
So maybe like you said,
the friend's band is a rock
and roll band, and it's
really loud and angry
and in your face, but for a
wedding, that's not appropriate.
So to tone it down means
to make it more appropriate
for the occasion, so maybe a less loud or
no offensive language or no swear words.
- Right, that's basically what
tone it down means, right?
If someone says you need to tone
it down, it's a little bit more direct.
Yeah, like you said, if
your parents tell you this,
it's maybe because you're
being a little bit too loud
or you're yelling or
you're being disrespectful.
So that's why your parents would tell
you, hey, you need to tone it down a bit.
- That's right, or sometimes
we have this in the office
where someone doesn't
understand how to
communicate in a positive
way, and so they say,
oh, that paper you did was really bad.
It was stupid, I don't
ever wanna see it again.
- Say, well, maybe you need
to tone it down a little bit.
Think about the words you're using
and make them a little bit less harsh.
- So kind of to relax, to reduce your level
of being aggressive, of being
loud, that's to tone it down.
- Exactly.
- Okay, a lot of great phrases there.
Why don't we now go back,
listen to our great dialogue
one last time, and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more.
(upbeat music)
- Trina, will you marry me?
- Yes, yes, yes.
Jared, of course I'll marry you.
- Oh babe, can't wait to spend
the rest of my life with you.
I can't wait for all
the adventures we're
gonna have for all the
fights and the laughter.
Can't wait to grow old
and wrinkly with you.
- Oh, Jared, I can't wait for our wedding.
I hope you don't mind, but
I've already chosen a date.
Six months from now in the summer.
Melissa saw you buying the ring last month,
so I had plenty of time to start planning.
- She what?
- Oh, don't worry, sweetie.
I didn't know when you
were going to propose.
It was still a nice surprise.
As I was saying, I got it all planned out.
There's almost nothing left to do.
I wrote up our guest list, and we
will have roughly 400 guests attending.
- 400?
- No need to sweat it.
My parents agreed to pay
for most of the wedding,
which is going to be
a low budget anyway.
So roughly 400 people,
which means that the whole
but Northwood Heights
will be our reception venue.
I thought it would be
nice if we had the wedding
at your parents' church, and my
uncle, of course, would be officiating.
We'll meet with him soon for
some pre-wedding counseling.
The music for the wedding
ceremony was a no-brainer.
My step sister and her string
quartet will take care of that.
My cousin will be the
official photographer.
I thought it would also be nice
if his daughter could sing a solo.
Did you know that she's going
to be professional opera singer?
- Uh.
- And then, of course,
the ladies at the church
would love to be our caters for the banquet
and will get the youth group to serve us.
I was thinking that your friend's band
could be our entertainment for the night,
though they might have to turn it
down a bit, or we could hire a DJ.
Your sister's husband
could get us a discount
with that company that
does the decor at weddings.
What's their name again?
I was thinking that we could
have an island paradise theme
wedding, and our theme color
would be a soothing blue-like
aquamarine, and there
will be a huge seashell
on the wall behind the podium
where we'll make our toast.
What do you think of small packages
of drink mixes for our wedding favors?
Who else am I missing?
Oh, your uncle could be our florist, and
his wife could make our wedding cake.
- Oh, wow.
- See, it's going to be wonderful.
Oh, this wedding is going to
be everything I ever dreamed of.
- If I survive the next six months.
- All right, so about weddings
and planning out a wedding.
Do you think 400 guests is a small wedding?
No, I think this woman is out of control.
In fact, in English, we
have a word for a bride,
or like a woman who's
getting married, that describes
someone who's completely
nuts about the wedding.
We call her a bridezilla.
- Brightzilla.
That's right, it's like Godzilla.
- Exactly, the movie
Godzilla, he's a monster.
- And he's out of control.
- He's out of control, and a bride
who's so obsessed with her wedding
that nothing else is
important, she's a bridezilla.
- Now it's a very big
thing for a woman, right,
for her wedding to be nice
and perfect and everything.
Do you think guys are
more relaxed in this sense?
- I don't know, I think
it depends on the guy.
As always, there are some
people who want to be
very involved and some
people who don't care.
But in general, I think men are
less worried about the details.
- There's just as long as
there's a wedding, it's fine.
- Exactly.
Although a lot of men, when the wedding
actually happens, start to get very nervous.
- Oh, but kind of like having
doubts, maybe cold feet.
- Yes, cold feet.
Like should I get married,
should I not get married?
- Oh, I think it's very interesting
because you see this in movies a lot.
And I've always wondered how often or how
common is it for a guy or a girl to say no
or to leave a wedding
when it has already started?
Because you have invited all these people,
all these friends and family, maybe people
came from different countries
and food is paid for venue.
You spend so much money on
a wedding and for you to say no.
I don't know how common it
is, it's very common in movies,
but I don't know anyone
who's experienced this.
- I don't either, actually,
now that you're bringing it up.
So maybe we could talk about this.
Is this common in your country?
First of all, do people spend
a lot of money on weddings?
And second of all, have
you ever heard of someone
actually leaving the
wedding before they finished?
- Yeah, during the
ceremony, not before, during.
- During the ceremony, so
our website is EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
Until next time.
Bye. (upbeat music)